{"tossups": [{"question": "The northern half of this peninsula was controlled in the 600s by an Exarchate [[EKS-ar-kate]] based in Ravenna. Hannibal Barca crossed the Alps with a mercenary army to raid this peninsula which hosts several microstates, including San Marino and Vatican City. For ten points, name this peninsula, the former home of the Etruscan civilization and the heart of the Roman Empire.", "answer": "<b><u>Italian</u></b> Peninsula (accept <b><u>Italic</u></b> Peninsula; accept <b><u>Apennine</u></b> Peninsula before \"Apennine\" is mentioned; accept <b><u>Italy</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This leader obtained a doctorate in quantum chemistry in 1986 prior to entering politics. This politician played a central role in negotiating the Treaty of Lisbon and was a main figure behind the stimulus plan to help shelter the European Union from the Great Recession. The leader of the Christian Democratic Union from 2000 to 2018, this politician was elected to her highest position in 2005. For ten points, name this first female chancellor of Germany.", "answer": "Angela <b><u>Merkel</u></b> (or Angela Dorothea <b><u>Merkel</u></b>; accept Angela Dorothea <b><u>Kasner</u></b>)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "Friedrich Miescher [[MEE-shuh]] first identified this molecule in 1869, calling it nuclein. Helicases create a \"fork\" during the replication of this molecule, whose structure was identified thanks to Rosalind Franklin's Photo 51. For ten points, name this molecule that is often sequenced, best identified by its double-helix structure documented by Watson and Crick.", "answer": "<b><u>DNA</u></b> (accept <b><u>Deoxyribonucleic acid</u></b>)", "metadata": "Science - Biology"}, {"question": "This man ordered the Hungnam Evacuation following his failure to predict an invasion by the People's Volunteer Army. This man's failure to abandon the strategically insignificant site of Peleliu [[peh-LEH-loo]] resulted in devastating losses for U.S. marines. This man's support of the use of nuclear weapons in the Korean War led to his sacking by Harry S. Truman. For ten points, name this Supreme Allied commander in the Pacific Theater.", "answer": "Douglas <b><u>MacArthur</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "The \"Plan of the Three Guarantees\" in this nation's city of Iguala established a short-lived Constitutional Monarchy there. The ransacking of a foreign chef's shop led to the First French Intervention in this nation during the Pastry War. This nation's war of independence began after the<em> Grito de Dolores</em> by Don Miguel Hidalgo. Much of New Spain was made up of, for ten points, what North American nation to the south of the United States?", "answer": "United States of <b><u>Mexico</u></b> (or Estados Unidos <b><u>Mexicanos</u></b>; accept <b><u>EUM</u></b>; accept First <b><u>Mexican</u></b> Empire; accept First <b><u>Mexican</u></b> Republic)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This one-time Minister of France refused to condemn the Reign of Terror saying it would \"Undermine the cause of republicanism in America.\" With James Madison, this man sponsored and wrote the<em> National Gazette</em> to raise money for his agrarian party. For ten points, name this Secretary of State in the first presidential cabinet, the rival of Alexander Hamilton and principal author of the Declaration of Independence.", "answer": "Thomas <b><u>Jefferson</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Ibn Battuta claimed that this structure's purpose was to keep out demonic beasts named Gog and Magog. The first sections of this structure were believed to have been built during the Spring and Autumn Period. The rebel Li Zicheng was defeated by a combined force of Manchus and General Wu Sangui's [[SAHNG-GWEES]] loyalists at this structure's namesake fortress in the Battle of Shanhai Pass. For ten points, name this series of fortifications across northern China.", "answer": "<b><u>Great Wall</u></b> of China (accept Wanli <b><u>Changcheng</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "In Islam, this book is identified with a pre-Islamic holy book titled<em> Zabur</em>. Portions of this book labelled<em> mizmor</em> were originally intended to be sung. Many sections of this book are attributed to Asaph and the Sons of Korah. The 23rd chapter of this book begins with the line \"The Lord is my shepherd, I shall not want.\" For ten points, name this Old Testament book that contains many poems attributed to King David.", "answer": "Book of <b><u>Psalms</u></b> (or The <b><u>Psalter</u></b>; accept <b><u>Tehillim</u></b>)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "The architects of this federal building were Cass Gilbert and Cass Gilbert Jr., and it was designated a National Historical Landmark in 1987. Prior to its completion in 1935, this building's main inhabitants worked in the Old Senate Chambers. Recent workers in this building include Elena Kagan, Neil Gorsuch, and Chief Justice John Roberts. For ten points, name this building in Washington D.C., home to the federal judicial branch.", "answer": "United States <b><u>Supreme Court</u></b> Building (accept the <b><u>Marble Palace</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This ruler met up with Maximilian I to defeat the French at the Battle of the Spurs, though he later took part in a peaceful celebration with Francis I at the Field of the Cloth of Gold. After supporting the Acts of Supremacy, this monarch presided over the dissolution of his country's monasteries. That occurred after this man broke from the Catholic Church in order to divorce Catherine of Aragon. For ten points, name this Tudor king of England, remembered for his six wives.", "answer": "<b><u>Henry VIII</u></b> [[the eighth]]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "The extinct great auk lived around the northern part of this ocean, and the Grand Banks in this ocean were a major center for cod fishing until their depletion in the 1990s. The navigator Himilco might have discovered this sea's Sargasso region in the 5th century BC. Most likely named for a certain globe-carrying Titan, for ten points, what is this ocean on which one finds the cities of Boston and New York?", "answer": "<b><u>Atlantic</u></b> Ocean", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This island's Sette Giugno [[seh-TAY JYOON-yoh]] holiday commemorates a British massacre of Italian irredentists. It's not Rhodes, but King George VI [[the sixth]] awarded this entire island the George Cross after it resisted Axis bombing campaigns. The image of Ottoman invincibility was shattered after the Knights Hospitaller successfully defended this island in 1565. Jean Parisot de Valette [[pah-ree-SOH duh-vah-LET]] names the capital of, for ten points, what small island nation to the south of Sicily?", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Malta</u></b> (or Repubblika ta' <b><u>Malta</u></b>; accept <b><u>Melita</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "During a 1781 raid, a force commanded by this man spared the main house at Berkeley Plantation, which he planned to appropriate for his own residence. This man arrived with relief troops to break the siege of Fort Stanwix and joined with Ethan Allen to capture Fort Ticonderoga. This major general later worked with John Andr\u00e9 in an attempt to surrender West Point. For ten points, name this Continental Army officer who defected to the British in 1780.", "answer": "Benedict <b><u>Arnold</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "A craze concerning this technology struck England in 1896 as people believed it had both beautification and germicidal properties. Until the 1950s, this technology was sold commercially to U.S. shoe stores to help associates size customers. Discoverer Wilhelm Roentgen [[VIL-helm RENT-gehn]] shouted \u201cI have seen my death!\u201d due to this invention revealing his hand's metacarpals and phalanges. For ten points, name this form of electromagnetic radiation often used to see if human bones are broken.", "answer": "<b><u>X-Ray</u></b> (accept <b><u>Roentgen</u></b> radiation before mentioned)", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Other Social Science"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>This politician signed the Mulford Act, against which the Black Panthers</u> <u>protested by marching on his capitol bearing arms. This man called in the National</u> <u>Guard to quell the People's Park Protest in the city of (+)</u> Berkeley. After impressing his fellow Republicans with a speech in support of Barry Goldwater, this man defeated Pat Brown to become the governor of California. (*)</b> For ten points, name this man who gave the \"Time for Choosing\" speech and was later elected president of the United States in 1980 and 1984.", "answer": "Ronald <b><u>Reagan</u></b> (or Ronald Wilson <b><u>Reagan</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>The Shapley-Curtis debate centered on whether or not this structure was a</u> <u>\"spiral nebula.\" The center of this structure contains a radio source discovered in</u> <u>1931 by Karl Jansky, the supermassive black hole Sagittarius (+)</u> A-star, and this structure was believed by the Babylonians to be the severed tail of a dragoness. Orbited by Large and Small Clouds named for (*)</b> Ferdinand Magellan, for ten points, what is this galaxy which is home to the Sun and Earth?", "answer": "<b><u>Milky Way</u></b> galaxy", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Astronomy"}, {"question": "<b><u>This city was founded in 1565 by Pedro Men\u00e9ndez de Avil\u00e9s [[ah-vee-LEHS]] on</u> <u>the feast day of the patron of brewers. Henry Flagler built a railroad through this city,</u> <u>which was annexed into the U.S. along with the rest of its state in the Adams-On\u00eds (+)</u> Treaty. This city was intended to be turned into a winter resort by an industrialist who constructed the Hotel Alcazar and Hotel Ponce de Leon. (*)</b> For ten points, name this Florida city, the oldest continuously-inhabited European settlement in the United States.", "answer": "<b><u>St. Augustine</u></b> (or <b><u>San Agust\u00edn</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>With his lover, this crown prince planned to flee to England and potentially</u> <u>usurp the throne from his father during the Katte [[KAH-tuh]] Affair. The failure of the</u> <u>Austrians and Russians to follow-up on the Battle of (+)</u> Kunesdorf was known as this king's \"Miracle of the House of Brandenburg.\" This German's victory in the Seven Years' War led to his country's annexation of (*)</b> Silesia. For ten points, name this \"Great\" king of Prussia during the mid-18th century.", "answer": "<b><u>Frederick</u></b> the Great (or <b><u>Friedrich</u></b> der Gro\u00dfe [[\"GROSS\"-uh]]; accept <b><u>Frederick</u> </b>II; or <b><u>Friedrich</u></b> II; accept <b><u>Old Fritz</u></b>; or Der <b><u>Alte Fritz</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>The mercenary group known as \"The Black Band\" fielded a contingent of men</u> <u>who wielded a</u></b><em><b><u> zweihander</u></b></em><b><u> [[ZVAI-hahn-duh]], a type of this weapon. Toyotomi</u> <u>Hideyoshi conducted \"hunts\" named (+)</u> for these weapons, which seized them from the peasantry to create a government monopoly on them. The</b><em><b> katana</b></em><b> and</b><em><b> rapier</b></em><b> are (*)</b> types of, for ten points, what sharp weapons often used for stabbing or cutting?", "answer": "<b><u>Sword</u></b>s (accept synonyms like <b><u>Blade</u></b>; accept specific swords like <b><u>katana</u></b> or <b><u>rapier</u></b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Scholars believe this mythic figure was syncretized with the Italic shepherd</u> <u>Garanus upon arrival to the Italian peninsula. Alongside Pompeii, a city bearing the</u> <u>name of this figure was partially preserved under the ash from the eruption of Mount</u></b> <b>(+)</b> <b>Vesuvius. Brandishing a lion skin pelt, the Roman emperor Commodus</b> <b>[[KAH-moh-dus]] often dressed as this mythic figure during his gladiatorial fights. (*) </b>For ten points, name this Roman demi-god and son of Jupiter, known for his immense strength.", "answer": "<b><u>Hercules</u></b> (accept <b><u>Heracles</u></b>; prompt on \"Herculaneum\")", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "<b><u>This country was listed as \"for sale\" on eBay in 2006, and bids reached nearly</u> <u>3,000 dollars before it was shut down. The 12-feet tall Giant Moa was hunted into</u> <u>extinction by Eastern Polynesian (+)</u> settlers who arrived in what is now this nation in the 15th century.</b><em><b> The Chronicles of Narnia</b></em><b> and</b><em><b> The Lord of the Rings</b></em><b> were primarily filmed in this country's (*)</b> North and South Islands. The British established the colonial capital of Auckland in, for ten points, which nation in Oceania?", "answer": "<b><u>New Zealand</u></b> (accept <b><u>Aotearoa</u></b>)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "<b><u>In the aftermath of this event, a building at Ignalina, Lithuania was closed by</u> <u>international agreement. The \"Red Forest\" was created by this event, after which a</u> <u>bubbler pool was (+)</u> drained thanks to the efforts of three engineers who were awarded the Order of Courage by Petro Poroshenko. Wildlife has run rampant in a 30-kilometer area called the Zone of Alienation (*)</b> that was created after this event. For ten points, name this nuclear disaster that occurred outside Pripyat [[PREE-pyat]], Ukraine.", "answer": "<b><u>Chernobyl</u></b> disaster (accept descriptive answers such as <b><u>Chernobyl</u></b> nuclear meltdown or <b><u>Chernobyl</u></b> nuclear disaster)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}], "bonuses": []}